We all want to eat
the kinds of foods
that make us feel
better and live longer.
But there’s so much conflicting
information out there,
so many nutrition opinions.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
It’s my job to give you
the information you need
to make the healthiest
choices possible.
Today we discover how plant-based
diets improve the performance
of athletes and
nonathletes alike.
In my video about comparing vegetarian
and vegan athletic performance,
endurance, and strength, I discussed
a 2020 study that found
that vegan athletes—even though
they were significantly older—
had significantly superior
aerobic capacity and endurance,
lasting 25 percent longer on a
time-to-exhaustion cycling test.
The question is why?
One potential mechanism
that could explain the greater level
of endurance performance
in vegans may be a higher amount
of carbohydrate intake, which could
lead to better endurance
performance through higher
muscle glycogen storage.
Other potential mechanisms
that may explain the better endurance
performance in vegans could
be due to the anti-oxidant
and anti-inflammatory
profiles of their diet.
Maybe it’s even their hearts.
Yet another study showing superior
VO2 max in vegan athletes,
meaning superior
aerobic capacity:
this time they also
did echocardiograms,
looking at their hearts
in real-time using ultrasound,
and the lower relative
wall thickness
and better main ventricle
systolic and diastolic function
in the vegans are most
likely positive ﬁndings.
Now wait a second. Given
the higher VO2 max reached
by the vegan athletes, maybe
they were just better trained
than the nonvegan athletes,
and that’s why their hearts
looked like they
were working better.
However, the weekly training
frequency and running distance
were similar in both groups,
suggesting benefits
even with the same
amount of training.
So, it’s important to educate
healthcare professionals;
so they don’t try
to discourage a vegan diet
and may even want to consider
telling folks implementing
an exercise training
program to give it a try.
But you don’t know if it
has the same kinds of effects
in nonathletes, until
you...put it to the test.
A vegetarian vs. conventional
calorie-restricted diet:
the effect on physical fitness
in response to aerobic exercise
in patients with
type 2 diabetes.
Diabetics were randomized
to the same caloric restriction,
the same exercise, but just
vegetarian versus nonvegetarian.
They provided all the meals
so they could ensure compliance
and closely monitored
the exercising.
VO2 max increased by 12 percent
in the vegetarian group,
significantly better than in
the non-vegetarian group
who didn’t significantly
improve at all.
Maximal performance increased
by 21 percent in the vegetarian group,
again, significantly better than in
the non-vegetarian group
who didn’t significantly
improve at all.
In other words, the results indicated
that more plant-based diets
led more effectively to
improvement in physical ﬁtness
than less plant-based diets,
after the same aerobic
exercise program.
It seems that those eating vegetarian
were able to better burn off
carbohydrates compared
to nonvegetarians,
and had better insulin sensitivity,
both markers of improved
metabolic ﬂexibility,
meaning the ability
to switch back and forth
between burning sugar and fat.
Besides physiological
mechanisms,
there may also be
psychological factors.
They observed reduced hunger
and reduced feelings of depression
in the vegetarian group
which may have given them
a more positive attitude
towards exercise.
Here’s the psychological data.
Those randomized to eat vegetarian
had a greater improvement
in quality of life and mood.
They felt less constrained,
meaning the calorie restriction
didn’t seem as burdensome;
they had less disinhibition,
meaning less tendency
to binge and overeat,
along with maybe
less feelings of hunger.
Not to mention the superior effects
of a vegetarian diet
on body weight, glycemic control,
blood lipids,
insulin sensitivity,
and oxidative stress.
Wait, better body weight?
I thought they were given
the same number of calories.
Yes, both diets were isocaloric,
the same calories,
yet just eating meat-free led
to significantly more weight loss—
about six pounds more;
more waist loss, a slimmer waist;
lower cholesterol, of course;
and less superficial fat,
meaning the external jiggly fat;
and most importantly, significantly
more visceral fat loss,
the most metabolically
dangerous deep belly fat.
Same calories, yet more
loss of body fat.
And not surprisingly,
better control of their diabetes.
All in addition to leading
more effectively
to improvements
in physical ﬁtness.
Did you know that long-
term plant-based eating
may improve exercise
capacity and endurance?
Here’s the story.
Few studies have investigated
the impact of a plant-based diet
on athletic performance, but
the majority of the studies
that have been done show no differences
in endurance, performance, or strength.
So, while plant-based diets
do not seem to provide advantages
or disadvantages
on exercise performance,
what plant-based diets can do
is reduce the risk of chronic disease.
This is a point
I made in my video
Why All Athletes Should
Eat Plant-Based Diets,
because surprisingly,
endurance athletes may have
more advanced atherosclerosis
and more heart muscle damage,
compared with sedentary individuals.
So, it’s even more important
they eat healthy.
But due to the favorable impact
on health,
it could be assumed that performance
would also be influenced
by plant-based diets.
Let’s take a closer look
at the available evidence.
This is the most commonly cited review.
Studies connecting vegetarian diets
to improved health
are well-established;
however, the evidence for this phenomenon
to be transferred
to improved physical performance
in athletes is less clear,
finding no differences
—at least acutely—
between a vegetarian-based diet
and an omnivorous diet
in muscular power, muscular strength,
short burst, or endurance performance.
The intervention studies in this review,
however, only lasted days or weeks.
So, being a vegetarian for four days
may not tip the balance,
or even a few months, but that’s
a considerable limitation.
These are people
who have been eating meat
their whole lives
and subsequently adopt
a vegetarian diet only
for the duration of the study,
rather than comparing participants
who have adhered to a vegetarian
or meat-containing diet long-term.
This study compared exercise capacity
of vegan, vegetarian,
and meat-eating recreational
runners and found
similar maximum power output
among all three groups,
suggesting there’s no significant difference
in maximum exercise capacity.
But that’s at the same training frequency,
time, and distance.
Perhaps plant-based diets
might enhance recovery
and allow such athletes
to train longer and harder?
A number of studies have come out
since this review
was published in 2016.
What’s the update?
Well, this study compared
the cardiorespiratory fitness
and peak torque strength differences
between vegetarian
and omnivore endurance athletes.
Most of the vegetarians
were actually vegans
and most or at least two years and…
results from this study indicate that
vegetarian endurance athletes’
cardiorespiratory ﬁtness
was greater than that for their
omnivorous counterparts.
They had a greater VO2 max,
meaning a greater maximal oxygen uptake,
greater aerobic capacity
as measured on a progressive,
graded, maximal treadmill test
to exhaustion,
though peak torque, peak strength
based on leg extensions
didn’t differ between diet groups.
Bottom line: these data suggest
that vegetarian diets
do not compromise
performance outcomes
and may facilitate
aerobic capacity in athletes.
In this 2020 study, all the plant-
based participants were eating vegan
for an average of four years.
So, they were essentially comparing
those who ate meat for 21 years
versus those who ate
meat for 25 years.
But after four years
eating plants,
you might expect to see
some sort of difference.
Yet, no signiﬁcant differences
were noted for upper
and lower body muscle strength,
like in the last new study.
Both groups of athletes were comparable
for total body weight
and lean body mass, though age
was signiﬁcantly higher in vegans
compared with omnivores;
so, that put them
at a little disadvantage.
Yet still, there it is again.
Significantly better aerobic capacity.
Then, they had them pedal
until exhaustion,
and the vegan group lasted
about 25 percent longer—
12 minutes as opposed to
9 minutes.
Is that just because their
aerobic capacity is so high?
No, even after controlling
for VO2 max levels, there was still
a signiﬁcant endurance advantage
in the vegans.
The researchers conclude
that in the very least,
a strictly plant-based diet
doesn’t seem to be detrimental
to endurance
and muscle strength,
and endurance might
actually be better in vegans,
contrary to popular belief.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the NutritionFacts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of How Not to Age.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.